<form>
    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>About Kea Unbound DDNS</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <type>info</type>
        <label>Documentation</label>
        <help>
<![CDATA[
<h4>Kea Unbound DDNS Integration</h4>

<p>Bridges Kea DHCP and Unbound DNS so hostnames resolve the moment a lease is issued,
without waiting for a DNS reload or manual entry.</p>

<h4>How It Works</h4>

<p><strong>DDNS Listener (real-time):</strong> Receives RFC 2136 DNS UPDATE packets from
kea-dhcp-ddns on <code>127.0.0.1:{{ port }}</code> and immediately registers or removes
A/AAAA and PTR records in Unbound. Records managed by Unbound Host Overrides are never
touched.</p>

<p><strong>Self-healing consistency:</strong> The resident daemon watches Kea and Unbound
service pidfiles. Whenever either service restarts (flushing runtime DNS records), the
daemon automatically runs a full reconcile from Kea — repopulating Unbound without any
manual intervention or PHP configure hook. The status banner above shows the current
reconcile state.</p>

<p><strong>Static Reservation Sync:</strong> Registers Kea static reservations in Unbound
before any client connects. Runs as part of each full reconcile and on demand via the
manual Sync button on the Lease Audit tab.</p>

<p><strong>Active Lease Sync:</strong> Bulk-syncs all active Kea leases into Unbound with
TTLs matching remaining lease time. Runs as part of each full reconcile and on demand via
the manual Sync button on the Lease Audit tab.</p>

<p><strong>DNS Record Cleaning:</strong> Periodically removes stale records not backed by
any active Kea lease, reservation, or Unbound Host Override. See the DNS Record Cleaning
settings below. The Lease Audit tab shows a full preview of what each cleanup would remove.</p>

<h4>Configuring Kea for DDNS</h4>

<p>Kea's DHCP-DDNS daemon must be running and forwarding updates to
<code>127.0.0.1:{{ port }}</code>. For each subnet, add to the Kea subnet config:</p>

<pre><code>"ddns-send-updates": true,
"ddns-override-no-update": true,
"ddns-override-client-update": true,
"hostname-char-replacement": "-"</code></pre>

<p>Use the <strong>Config Check</strong> tab to verify Unbound and Kea DHCP configuration.</p>

<h4>Tabs</h4>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Settings:</strong> Enable the plugin; configure sync, cleanup, and listen port</li>
  <li><strong>Config Check:</strong> Verify Unbound DNS settings and Kea subnet DDNS configuration</li>
  <li><strong>Lease Audit:</strong> Inspect all DNS records, preview and run cleanup, trigger syncs</li>
  <li><strong>Log File:</strong> Daemon, sync, audit, and cleanup logs</li>
</ul>
]]>
        </help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>Service</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.enabled</id>
        <label>Enabled</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Enable Kea to Unbound DNS registration. When enabled, DNS UPDATE packets from kea-dhcp-ddns are received and translated into Unbound local_data entries.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>DNS Synchronization</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.synthesize_ptr</id>
        <label>Synthesize PTR records</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Automatically create the standard in-addr.arpa / ip6.arpa PTR (reverse) record for every A/AAAA update received from kea-dhcp-ddns. Enabled by default — PTRs work immediately without needing a reverse zone in kea-dhcp-ddns. Disable only if you manage reverse DNS separately (e.g. another authoritative server for in-addr.arpa). Explicit PTR updates from kea-dhcp-ddns are always applied regardless of this setting. When both this option and a kea-dhcp-ddns reverse zone are configured for a subnet, PTRs are written by both paths — harmless, but the Config Check tab will flag it per subnet.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.collision_policy</id>
        <label>Hostname collision policy</label>
        <type>dropdown</type>
        <help><![CDATA[Action when a hostname is already registered in Unbound for a
        different IP address.<br><br>
        <b>Last wins</b> (default): the existing record is removed and replaced by the new
        one. Correct behaviour for most networks — Kea issues the new IP and DDNS updates
        Unbound atomically.<br>
        <b>Allow</b>: both records coexist — Unbound will round-robin between them. Use
        when you want multiple IPs per hostname (e.g. dual-stack hosts with separate
        DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 leases).<br>
        <b>First wins</b>: the existing record is kept; the new registrant is rejected.
        Static reservations are always synced before dynamic leases, so First wins
        naturally protects reservation DNS entries from being overwritten by dynamic
        clients. Best-effort on reconcile after restart (ordering is deterministic within
        a run, not across restarts).<br>
        <b>None</b>: on any dynamic conflict, no dynamic lease gets the bare hostname —
        existing dynamic records for that name are deleted. The hostname becomes available
        again once all competing leases expire and a new lease registers. Useful when
        hostname conflicts indicate misconfiguration and you want conflicts to be silent
        rather than resolved arbitrarily.<br><br>
        Note: this plugin does not store or validate DHCID records. Collision detection
        is based on name-to-IP conflicts in Unbound, not client identity.]]></help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.magic_names</id>
        <label>Magic hostnames</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help><![CDATA[When enabled, every host involved in a hostname collision receives an
        additional disambiguated forward record alongside whatever the collision policy
        determines for the bare hostname. The magic hostname encodes the hardware
        identifier type and last 6 characters of the identifier:<br><br>
        <code>laptop-mAABBCC</code> — MAC-identified host (last 3 octets)<br>
        <code>laptop-dAABBCC</code> — DUID-identified host<br>
        <code>laptop-i001050</code> — IP-only host override (last 2 octets, 3-padded)<br><br>
        Magic hostnames are not removed eagerly when a collision resolves — they persist
        until the lease expires naturally, so cached references (SSH sessions, monitoring)
        remain valid. Enable <b>LAA tagging</b> below to mark devices using randomized
        MACs (iOS, Android) with an extra <code>-laa-</code> infix.]]></help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.write_magic_ptrs</id>
        <label>Magic PTR records</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help><![CDATA[When enabled, PTR (reverse) records for dynamic lease IPs in a
        collision group point to the magic FQDN rather than the bare hostname. Every IP
        in the group gets a stable, unambiguous PTR that never changes as collision
        winners rotate:<br><br>
        <code>101.1.168.192.in-addr.arpa PTR laptop-mAABBCC.home.lan.</code><br><br>
        When disabled (default), PTR behaviour is unchanged from non-magic mode: the
        collision winner gets PTR to the bare hostname, losers get no PTR record. The
        mixed state (winner bare, losers magic) is deliberately avoided — PTR targets
        would otherwise change each time the collision winner rotates.<br><br>
        Requires both <b>Magic hostnames</b> and <b>Synthesize PTR records</b> to be
        enabled. Note: magic PTRs cause a mismatch between the hostname in a TLS
        certificate (issued for the bare hostname) and the PTR returned by a reverse
        lookup, which can break tools that perform reverse-lookup certificate
        verification.]]></help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.magic_laa_tag</id>
        <label>LAA tagging for magic hostnames</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help><![CDATA[When enabled alongside magic hostnames, devices whose MAC address has
        the locally administered bit set (IEEE 802c / RFC 9724) receive an
        <code>-laa-</code> infix in their magic hostname:<br><br>
        <code>laptop-laa-mAABBCC</code><br><br>
        LAA MACs are assigned by the device itself (not the manufacturer) and are commonly
        used for MAC randomization on iOS, Android, and Windows. The infix signals that the
        suffix may not be stable across reconnections — the device may rotate its MAC per
        network or per day. Do not use LAA magic hostnames in long-lived references such
        as TLS certificates or SSH <code>known_hosts</code> entries.]]></help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>DNS Record Cleaning</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.clean_stale_records</id>
        <label>Clean stale records after restart</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>After each full reconcile triggered by a Kea or Unbound restart, sweep Unbound for records no longer backed by any Kea reservation or active lease and remove them immediately. Useful when static reservations are removed — the stale DNS records disappear on the next restart rather than waiting for the scheduled auto-clean.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.enable_auto_clean</id>
        <label>Enable scheduled sync / clean</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Run Kea→Unbound sync and/or stale-record cleaning on a schedule. Use the sub-options below to choose what runs. The frequency and hour fields below control when jobs fire.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.cron_run_sync</id>
        <label>Full sync</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Reconcile all Kea leases and reservations into Unbound at each scheduled interval. Catches any drift the live path or log watcher missed — including new leases registered while kea-dhcp-ddns was temporarily down. Only active when scheduled sync / clean is enabled.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.cron_run_clean</id>
        <label>Clean stale records</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Remove Unbound records not backed by any active Kea lease, reservation, or Unbound Host Override — primarily records left behind by leases that expired without an explicit release. Review the Lease Audit tab to preview what would be removed. Only active when scheduled sync / clean is enabled.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.auto_clean_interval</id>
        <label>Schedule frequency</label>
        <type>dropdown</type>
        <help>How often to run the scheduled sync and/or clean. The manual Sync and Clean buttons on the Lease Audit tab run the same operations on demand.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.auto_clean_hour</id>
        <label>Schedule hour (0–23)</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <hint>0</hint>
        <help>Hour of the day (0–23, UTC) for the daily scheduled run. Only used when frequency is set to "Daily".</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.enable_logwatch</id>
        <label>Enable log watcher</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Enable a secondary daemon that tails the Kea DHCP log and the listener log for events the live DDNS path missed. Use the sub-options below to choose which events trigger action. Requires Kea's kea-dhcp4 / kea-dhcp6 loggers at INFO severity or lower writing to /var/log/kea/ — the OPNsense default. Off by default — the scheduled sync covers most deployments without it.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.logwatch_on_release</id>
        <label>Purge IP on lease release</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>When a DHCP4_RELEASE or DHCP6_RELEASE is seen in the Kea log, immediately purge all DNS records for that IP. This is the fastest path to removing stale forward and reverse records when a device explicitly releases its lease. Only active when Log Watcher is enabled.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.logwatch_on_servfail</id>
        <label>Re-sync names after listener SERVFAIL</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>When the DDNS listener returns SERVFAIL (Unbound briefly unavailable or locked during an update), trigger a targeted kea-sync for the affected names. Supplements the dirty-name drain so missed adds and removes recover quickly rather than waiting for the next scheduled sync. Only active when Log Watcher is enabled.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.logwatch_on_missed_remove</id>
        <label>Re-sync on missed DNS removes</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help><![CDATA[When a DNS Remove is seen in the listener log without a corresponding Add within a short grace window, trigger a targeted kea-sync for that hostname. Closes the LEASE_REUSE gap: when kea-dhcp-ddns sends a CHG_REMOVE for a hostname/IP and then skips the follow-up Add (because the lease looks unchanged to D2), the DNS record disappears until the next scheduled sync. With this option on, the gap is closed within seconds. Only active when Log Watcher is enabled.]]></help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>Kea-Unbound DDNS Listener</label>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.port</id>
        <label>Port</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <hint>53535</hint>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>UDP port to listen on for DNS UPDATE packets from kea-dhcp-ddns. Must match the destination port configured in kea-dhcp-ddns. Default 53535.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>Advanced</label>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.max_full_sync_attempts</id>
        <label>Max reconcile attempts</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <hint>5</hint>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>How many failed full reconcile attempts are allowed before the daemon marks itself degraded (alert banner) and stops retrying. 0 means retry indefinitely. Default 5.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.readiness_watchdog_minutes</id>
        <label>Readiness watchdog (minutes)</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <hint>10</hint>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Minutes to wait for Kea and Unbound to become ready after startup before the watchdog terminates the daemon (daemon(8) will restart it). 0 disables the watchdog. Default 10.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>Unbound Memory Recovery</label>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.enable_fast_reload</id>
        <label>Enable daemon-triggered recovery</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help><![CDATA[After the NCR threshold below is reached, the daemon calls
        <code>unbound-control fast-reload</code> to reclaim heap memory fragmented by
        repeated local_data add and remove calls, then immediately runs a full Kea sync
        to repopulate records. Falls back to <code>unbound-control reload</code> on
        Unbound older than 1.22. This controls only the daemon NCR counter — the
        scheduled recovery job below is independent and has its own toggle.]]></help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.fast_reload_threshold</id>
        <label>NCR threshold</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <hint>5000</hint>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Number of live-path DNS UPDATE packets (NCRs) returning NOERROR before the daemon triggers a fast-reload. Each NCR typically generates 1-3 unbound-control calls. Range 100-100000. Default 5000. Only active when fast-reload is enabled.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.enable_fast_reload_cron</id>
        <label>Enable scheduled recovery</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Run a cron job that triggers fast-reload on a fixed schedule, independent of the daemon NCR counter. Catches the case where the daemon restarts (resetting its counter) but Unbound keeps running, allowing memory to accumulate indefinitely.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.fast_reload_cron_days</id>
        <label>Scheduled recovery interval</label>
        <type>dropdown</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>How often the scheduled recovery cron job fires. Only active when scheduled recovery is enabled.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.fast_reload_cron_hour</id>
        <label>Scheduled recovery time (hour)</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <hint>3</hint>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Hour of day (0–23) at which the scheduled recovery cron job fires. Default is 3 (03:00). Only active when scheduled recovery is enabled.</help>
    </field>

</form>
