<form>
    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>About Kea Unbound DDNS</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <type>info</type>
        <label>Documentation</label>
        <help>
<![CDATA[
<h4>Kea Unbound DDNS Integration</h4>

<p>This plugin bridges Kea DHCP and Unbound DNS so hostnames resolve as soon as a device
is assigned an address — without waiting for a DNS reload or manual entry.</p>

<h4>How It Works</h4>

<p><strong>DDNS Listener (real-time):</strong> A background daemon listens for DNS UPDATE
packets (RFC 2136) sent by Kea's DHCP-DDNS service on <code>127.0.0.1:{{ port }}</code>.
Each time a client receives a lease, Kea notifies the daemon, which immediately registers
the forward (A/AAAA) and reverse (PTR) record in Unbound. When a lease expires or is
released, Kea sends a DELETE and the records are removed. This path handles the common
case; the sync and cleanup paths below handle edge cases and recovery.</p>

<p><strong>Static Reservation Sync:</strong> When enabled, Kea static reservations are
registered in Unbound immediately — before any client connects — so the hostname resolves
whether or not the device is online. Names already managed by OPNsense via Unbound Host
Overrides are skipped. Fires automatically on Kea start, Kea config change, and Unbound
reload; also available as a manual button on the Lease Audit tab.</p>

<p><strong>Active Lease Sync:</strong> When enabled, all active Kea leases are synced into
Unbound with TTLs set to the remaining lease lifetime. This repopulates Unbound after a
restart and catches any leases the DDNS stream may have missed (e.g. leases issued while
the daemon was down). Fires automatically on Kea start, Kea config change, and Unbound
reload; also available as a manual button on the Lease Audit tab.</p>

<h4>DNS Record Cleaning</h4>

<p>Kea's DDNS protocol is ADD-heavy: it reliably sends ADDs when a new IP is issued but
does not always send a DELETE for the old IP when a client moves to a new address. Two
complementary cleanup mechanisms handle the resulting drift:</p>

<p><strong>Clean up old IPs on lease update (per-hostname, fires on every ADD):</strong>
Each time a new IP is registered for a hostname via DDNS, the daemon immediately checks
whether that hostname has any older IPs in Unbound that Kea no longer recognises. If so,
they are removed along with their PTR records. This is best-effort — the ADD and the DDNS
response always succeed regardless of cleanup outcome. Records managed by Unbound Host
Overrides are never touched.</p>

<p><strong>Scheduled bulk cleanup (all of Unbound vs. all of Kea):</strong> Periodically
compares every record in Unbound's runtime local data against every Kea lease, reservation,
and Unbound Host Override. Any record not backed by one of those sources is removed. Requires
full Kea data to be available; if Kea is unreachable the bulk clean is skipped to avoid
removing records it cannot verify. The <strong>Clean Stale Records</strong> button on the
Lease Audit tab runs the same operation on demand. Use the Lease Audit tab to preview
exactly which records would be removed before enabling scheduled cleanup.</p>

<h4>Configuring Kea for DDNS</h4>

<p>For this plugin to work, Kea DHCP must be configured to send DDNS updates. This is a
two-part process:</p>

<p><strong>1. Enable DHCP-DDNS Daemon</strong><br/>
Kea's DHCP-DDNS daemon must be running and configured to forward updates to
<code>127.0.0.1:{{ port }}</code>.</p>

<p><strong>2. Configure Subnets for DDNS</strong><br/>
For each subnet where you want DDNS, add this to the subnet configuration in Kea:</p>

<pre><code>"subnet4": [
  {
    "subnet": "10.0.0.0/24",
    "ddns-send-updates": true,
    "ddns-override-no-update": true,
    "ddns-override-client-update": true,
    "hostname-char-replacement": "-",
    ...
  }
]</code></pre>

<p><strong>Settings explained:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><code>ddns-send-updates</code>: Enable DDNS for this subnet (required)</li>
  <li><code>ddns-override-no-update</code>: Register even if the client opts out (recommended)</li>
  <li><code>ddns-override-client-update</code>: Always register PTR records (recommended)</li>
  <li><code>hostname-char-replacement</code>: Replace invalid characters in hostnames (optional, <code>"-"</code> recommended)</li>
</ul>

<p>Use the <strong>Kea Config Check</strong> tab to verify which subnets are configured for
DDNS and that the DDNS daemon is pointing at the correct address and port.</p>

<h4>Features</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Real-time registration:</strong> Hostnames resolve the moment a lease is issued, via RFC 2136 DDNS</li>
  <li><strong>Dual-stack:</strong> Full IPv4 (A) and IPv6 (AAAA) support with matching PTR records</li>
  <li><strong>Static reservations:</strong> Pre-register Kea reservations in DNS before any client connects</li>
  <li><strong>Drift correction:</strong> Two cleanup paths remove stale records Kea never explicitly deleted</li>
  <li><strong>Lease Audit:</strong> Full visibility into every DNS record — what's live, what's backed by Kea, what's stale</li>
  <li><strong>Host Override safety:</strong> Records managed by Unbound Host Overrides are never modified or removed</li>
  <li><strong>TSIG Authentication:</strong> Optional TSIG signing on DDNS updates (advanced)</li>
  <li><strong>OPNsense integration:</strong> Service control, cron scheduling, and syslog via standard OPNsense hooks</li>
</ul>

<h4>Tabs</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Settings:</strong> Enable the plugin, configure sync and cleanup behaviour, set TSIG options</li>
  <li><strong>Kea Config Check:</strong> Verify which Kea subnets have DDNS configured and that the DDNS daemon is correctly pointed at this plugin</li>
  <li><strong>Lease Audit:</strong> Inspect every DNS record in Unbound with its Kea backing status. Preview and run stale record cleanup. Manually trigger syncs.</li>
  <li><strong>Log File:</strong> Live and historical logs for the daemon, sync, audit, and cleanup operations</li>
</ul>
]]>
        </help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>Service</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.enabled</id>
        <label>Enabled</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Enable Kea to Unbound DNS registration. When enabled, DNS UPDATE packets from kea-dhcp-ddns are received and translated into Unbound local_data entries.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>DNS Synchronization</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.sync_static_reservations</id>
        <label>Sync Kea static reservations to Unbound</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Register Kea static reservations in Unbound DNS so they resolve immediately (before any client connects). Names already managed by OPNsense in Unbound (Host Overrides, or "Register DHCP Static Mappings") are skipped, so this is safe whether or not that Unbound setting is on. Requires the Kea DHCP service (kea-dhcp4/kea-dhcp6) to be running.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <id>general.general.sync_dynamic_leases</id>
        <label>Sync Kea active leases to Unbound</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Register Kea active leases in Unbound DNS with TTL matching lease expiration. Repopulates Unbound on startup and refreshes entries periodically. Requires the Kea DHCP service (kea-dhcp4/kea-dhcp6) to be running.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>DNS Record Cleaning</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.aggressive_cleanup</id>
        <label>Clean up old IPs on lease update</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>When a new DHCP lease is registered via DDNS UPDATE, remove any previous IP addresses for that hostname that are no longer in Kea's lease or reservation table. This handles the common case where Kea issues a client a new IP without sending a DNS DELETE for the old one (standard Kea behaviour on IP change). Best-effort: the ADD is always recorded and the DDNS response is always sent regardless of whether cleanup succeeds. Requires Kea to be reachable at the time of the update. Records managed by Unbound Host Overrides are never touched.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.enable_auto_clean</id>
        <label>Automatically clean stale DNS records</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Periodically compare all of Unbound's runtime DNS records against all Kea leases, reservations, and Unbound Host Overrides, and remove any record not backed by one of those sources. Requires Kea to be reachable; the job is skipped if Kea is unavailable. Warning: this removes ANY A/AAAA/PTR record in Unbound's runtime local-data not backed by Kea or an Unbound Host Override — records injected by another tool or script will be erased. Use the Lease Audit tab to preview exactly what would be removed before enabling this.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.auto_clean_interval</id>
        <label>Auto-clean frequency</label>
        <type>dropdown</type>
        <help>How often to run the scheduled bulk cleanup. Only used when auto-clean is enabled. The manual Clean button on the Lease Audit tab runs the same operation on demand.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>Kea-Unbound DDNS Listener</label>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.port</id>
        <label>Port</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <hint>53535</hint>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>UDP port to listen on for DNS UPDATE packets from kea-dhcp-ddns. Must match the destination port configured in kea-dhcp-ddns. Default 53535.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>TSIG Authentication</label>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
    </field>
    <field>
        <type>info</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <label>Status</label>
        <help><![CDATA[<span class="text-warning"><strong>TSIG authentication has not been tested in this release and is disabled.</strong> The listener only accepts connections from 127.0.0.1, so unsigned updates from kea-dhcp-ddns are safe on a single host. These fields are shown for reference only.</span>]]></help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.enable_tsig</id>
        <label>Enable TSIG authentication</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Require TSIG signatures on DNS UPDATE packets from kea-dhcp-ddns. When disabled, packets are accepted unsigned (safe since the listener only accepts connections from 127.0.0.1). When enabled, kea-dhcp-ddns must be configured to sign updates with the matching key name and algorithm below. NOTE: Changes to TSIG settings require clicking "Apply" to restart the daemon and take effect.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.tsig_key_name</id>
        <label>TSIG Key Name</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Name of the TSIG key. kea-dhcp-ddns must be configured to sign updates with this exact key name. Only used when TSIG is enabled.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.tsig_key_secret</id>
        <label>TSIG Key Secret</label>
        <type>password</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Base64-encoded HMAC secret. Must match the secret configured in kea-dhcp-ddns. Only used when TSIG is enabled.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.tsig_algorithm</id>
        <label>TSIG Algorithm</label>
        <type>dropdown</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Algorithm used to sign DNS UPDATE packets. Must match the algorithm configured in kea-dhcp-ddns. HMAC-SHA256 is recommended. Only used when TSIG is enabled.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>Kea Service Control Connection</label>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
    </field>
    <field>
        <type>info</type>
        <label>Status</label>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help><![CDATA[
<strong>Reserved for future use.</strong> The plugin currently connects to the
Kea daemons automatically: it reads the active Kea configuration to find each
daemon's control socket (unix socket or HTTP listener) and falls back to the
standard OPNsense control sockets. The fields below are disabled and not yet
honored — they are placeholders for a future release that will let you override
the connection manually.]]></help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.mode</id>
        <label>Connection mode</label>
        <type>dropdown</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>How to reach the Kea daemons. Auto-detect reads the running Kea configuration.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.dhcp4_socket</id>
        <label>DHCPv4 unix socket</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Path to the kea-dhcp4 control socket (used when mode is Unix socket).</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.dhcp6_socket</id>
        <label>DHCPv6 unix socket</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Path to the kea-dhcp6 control socket (used when mode is Unix socket).</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.dhcp4_http_host</id>
        <label>DHCPv4 HTTP host</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Host of the kea-dhcp4 HTTP control listener (used when mode is HTTP).</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.dhcp4_http_port</id>
        <label>DHCPv4 HTTP port</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Port of the kea-dhcp4 HTTP control listener (default 8004).</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.dhcp6_http_host</id>
        <label>DHCPv6 HTTP host</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Host of the kea-dhcp6 HTTP control listener (used when mode is HTTP).</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.dhcp6_http_port</id>
        <label>DHCPv6 HTTP port</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Port of the kea-dhcp6 HTTP control listener (default 8006).</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.http_tls</id>
        <label>Use HTTPS</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Connect to the HTTP control listener over TLS.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.http_tls_verify</id>
        <label>Verify TLS certificate</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Verify the daemon's TLS certificate. Leave off for self-signed OPNsense control certificates.</help>
    </field>

</form>
