<form>
    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>About Kea Unbound DDNS</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <type>info</type>
        <label>Documentation</label>
        <help>
<![CDATA[
<h4>Kea Unbound DDNS Integration</h4>

<p>Bridges Kea DHCP and Unbound DNS so hostnames resolve the moment a lease is issued,
without waiting for a DNS reload or manual entry.</p>

<h4>How It Works</h4>

<p><strong>DDNS Listener (real-time):</strong> Receives RFC 2136 DNS UPDATE packets from
kea-dhcp-ddns on <code>127.0.0.1:{{ port }}</code> and immediately registers or removes
A/AAAA and PTR records in Unbound. Records managed by Unbound Host Overrides are never
touched.</p>

<p><strong>Self-healing consistency:</strong> The resident daemon watches Kea and Unbound
service pidfiles. Whenever either service restarts (flushing runtime DNS records), the
daemon automatically runs a full reconcile from Kea — repopulating Unbound without any
manual intervention or PHP configure hook. The status banner above shows the current
reconcile state.</p>

<p><strong>Static Reservation Sync:</strong> Registers Kea static reservations in Unbound
before any client connects. Runs as part of each full reconcile and on demand via the
manual Sync button on the Lease Audit tab.</p>

<p><strong>Active Lease Sync:</strong> Bulk-syncs all active Kea leases into Unbound with
TTLs matching remaining lease time. Runs as part of each full reconcile and on demand via
the manual Sync button on the Lease Audit tab.</p>

<p><strong>DNS Record Cleaning:</strong> Periodically removes stale records not backed by
any active Kea lease, reservation, or Unbound Host Override. See the DNS Record Cleaning
settings below. The Lease Audit tab shows a full preview of what each cleanup would remove.</p>

<h4>Configuring Kea for DDNS</h4>

<p>Kea's DHCP-DDNS daemon must be running and forwarding updates to
<code>127.0.0.1:{{ port }}</code>. For each subnet, add to the Kea subnet config:</p>

<pre><code>"ddns-send-updates": true,
"ddns-override-no-update": true,
"ddns-override-client-update": true,
"hostname-char-replacement": "-"</code></pre>

<p>Use the <strong>Kea Config Check</strong> tab to verify subnet DDNS configuration.</p>

<h4>Tabs</h4>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Settings:</strong> Enable the plugin; configure sync, cleanup, and listen port</li>
  <li><strong>Kea Config Check:</strong> Verify DDNS is configured in Kea subnets</li>
  <li><strong>Lease Audit:</strong> Inspect all DNS records, preview and run cleanup, trigger syncs</li>
  <li><strong>Log File:</strong> Daemon, sync, audit, and cleanup logs</li>
</ul>
]]>
        </help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>Service</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.enabled</id>
        <label>Enabled</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Enable Kea to Unbound DNS registration. When enabled, DNS UPDATE packets from kea-dhcp-ddns are received and translated into Unbound local_data entries.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>DNS Synchronization</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.sync_static_reservations</id>
        <label>Sync Kea static reservations to Unbound</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Register Kea static reservations in Unbound DNS so they resolve immediately (before any client connects). Names already managed by OPNsense in Unbound (Host Overrides, or "Register DHCP Static Mappings") are skipped, so this is safe whether or not that Unbound setting is on. Requires the Kea DHCP service (kea-dhcp4/kea-dhcp6) to be running.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <id>general.general.sync_dynamic_leases</id>
        <label>Sync Kea active leases to Unbound</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Register Kea active leases in Unbound DNS with TTL matching lease expiration. Repopulates Unbound on startup and after each Kea or Unbound restart. Requires the Kea DHCP service (kea-dhcp4/kea-dhcp6) to be running.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>DNS Record Cleaning</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.synthesize_ptr</id>
        <label>Synthesize PTR records from DDNS updates</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Automatically create the standard in-addr.arpa / ip6.arpa PTR (reverse) record for every A/AAAA update received from kea-dhcp-ddns. Enabled by default — PTRs work immediately without needing a reverse zone in kea-dhcp-ddns. Disable only if you manage reverse DNS separately (e.g. another authoritative server for in-addr.arpa). Explicit PTR updates from kea-dhcp-ddns are always applied regardless of this setting. When both this option and a kea-dhcp-ddns reverse zone are configured for a subnet, PTRs are written by both paths — harmless, but the Kea Config Check tab will flag it per subnet.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.collision_policy</id>
        <label>Hostname collision policy</label>
        <type>dropdown</type>
        <help><![CDATA[Action when a hostname is already registered in Unbound for a
        different IP address.<br><br>
        <b>Last wins</b> (default): the existing record is removed and replaced by the new
        one. Correct behaviour for most networks — Kea issues the new IP and DDNS updates
        Unbound atomically.<br>
        <b>Allow</b>: both records coexist — Unbound will round-robin between them. Use
        when you want multiple IPs per hostname (e.g. dual-stack hosts with separate
        DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 leases).<br>
        <b>First wins</b>: the existing record is kept; the new registrant is rejected.
        Static reservations are always synced before dynamic leases, so First wins
        naturally protects reservation DNS entries from being overwritten by dynamic
        clients. Best-effort on reconcile after restart (ordering is deterministic within
        a run, not across restarts).<br><br>
        Note: this plugin does not store or validate DHCID records. Collision detection
        is based on name-to-IP conflicts in Unbound, not client identity.]]></help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.enable_auto_clean</id>
        <label>Automatically clean stale DNS records</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Periodically compare all of Unbound's runtime DNS records against all Kea leases, reservations, and Unbound Host Overrides, and remove any record not backed by one of those sources. Requires Kea to be reachable; the job is skipped if Kea is unavailable. Warning: this removes ANY A/AAAA/PTR record in Unbound's runtime local-data not backed by Kea or an Unbound Host Override — records injected by another tool or script will be erased. Use the Lease Audit tab to preview exactly what would be removed before enabling this.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.auto_clean_interval</id>
        <label>Auto-clean frequency</label>
        <type>dropdown</type>
        <help>How often to run the scheduled bulk cleanup. Only used when auto-clean is enabled. The manual Clean button on the Lease Audit tab runs the same operation on demand.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.auto_clean_hour</id>
        <label>Auto-clean hour (0–23)</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <hint>0</hint>
        <help>Hour of the day (0–23, UTC) to run the daily auto-clean. Only used when frequency is set to "Daily".</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>Kea-Unbound DDNS Listener</label>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.port</id>
        <label>Port</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <hint>53535</hint>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>UDP port to listen on for DNS UPDATE packets from kea-dhcp-ddns. Must match the destination port configured in kea-dhcp-ddns. Default 53535.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>Advanced</label>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.dirty_set_cap</id>
        <label>Dirty-set cap</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <hint>100</hint>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Maximum number of deferred hostname updates tracked before the next reconcile becomes a full sync. Lower values reduce targeted-drain scope at high churn. Default 100.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.max_full_sync_attempts</id>
        <label>Max reconcile attempts</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <hint>5</hint>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>How many failed full reconcile attempts are allowed before the daemon marks itself degraded (alert banner) and stops retrying. 0 means retry indefinitely. Default 5.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.readiness_watchdog_minutes</id>
        <label>Readiness watchdog (minutes)</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <hint>10</hint>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Minutes to wait for Kea and Unbound to become ready after startup before the watchdog terminates the daemon (daemon(8) will restart it). 0 disables the watchdog. Default 10.</help>
    </field>

</form>
