<form>
    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>About Kea Unbound DDNS</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <type>info</type>
        <label>Documentation</label>
        <help>
<![CDATA[
<h4>Kea Unbound DDNS Integration</h4>

<p>This plugin creates a bridge between Kea DHCP and Unbound DNS, allowing DHCP leases and static reservations to be automatically registered in DNS.</p>

<h4>How It Works</h4>

<p><strong>Static Reservations:</strong> When you create a static DHCP reservation in Kea, this plugin automatically registers it in Unbound DNS (A/AAAA and PTR records). This happens immediately when the plugin is enabled, without waiting for any client to connect.</p>

<p><strong>Dynamic Leases:</strong> When a client receives a DHCP lease from Kea, the lease information is registered in Unbound DNS with a TTL matching the lease expiration time. This ensures DNS records automatically expire when leases expire.</p>

<p><strong>DDNS Protocol:</strong> The plugin implements RFC 2136 DNS UPDATE, receiving DNS update requests from Kea's DHCP-DDNS daemon and translating them into Unbound local_data entries.</p>

<h4>Configuring Kea for DDNS</h4>

<p>For this plugin to work, you must configure Kea DHCP to send DDNS updates. This is a two-part process:</p>

<p><strong>1. Enable DHCP-DDNS Daemon</strong><br/>
Kea's DHCP-DDNS daemon must be running and configured to send updates to this server (127.0.0.1:{{ port }}).</p>

<p><strong>2. Configure Subnets for DDNS</strong><br/>
For each subnet where you want DDNS, add this to the subnet configuration in Kea:</p>

<pre><code>"subnet4": [
  {
    "subnet": "10.0.0.0/24",
    "ddns-send-updates": true,
    "ddns-override-no-update": true,
    "ddns-override-client-update": true,
    "hostname-char-replacement": "-",
    ...
  }
]</code></pre>

<p><strong>Settings explained:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><code>ddns-send-updates</code>: Enable DDNS for this subnet (required)</li>
  <li><code>ddns-override-no-update</code>: Send updates even if client requests not to (recommended)</li>
  <li><code>ddns-override-client-update</code>: Always update PTR records (recommended)</li>
  <li><code>hostname-char-replacement</code>: Replace invalid chars in hostnames (optional, "-" recommended)</li>
</ul>

<p>Use the <strong>Kea Config Check</strong> tab to verify which subnets are configured for DDNS.</p>

<h4>Features</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Dual-stack:</strong> Supports both IPv4 (A records) and IPv6 (AAAA records)</li>
  <li><strong>PTR Records:</strong> Automatically generates reverse DNS (PTR) records</li>
  <li><strong>Self-healing:</strong> Leases automatically expire from DNS when their TTL expires</li>
  <li><strong>TSIG Authentication:</strong> Optional TSIG signing for secure updates</li>
  <li><strong>Audit & Cleanup:</strong> Tools to verify DNS status and clean up stale records</li>
  <li><strong>OPNsense Integration:</strong> Fully integrated with OPNsense services and configuration</li>
</ul>

<h4>Tabs</h4>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Settings:</strong> Configure plugin behavior, enable/disable sync, set TSIG options</li>
  <li><strong>Kea Config Check:</strong> View which Kea subnets are configured for DDNS</li>
  <li><strong>Lease Audit:</strong> View all registered DNS entries and their status</li>
  <li><strong>Log File:</strong> View plugin logs for troubleshooting</li>
</ul>
]]>
        </help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>Service</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.enabled</id>
        <label>Enabled</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Enable Kea to Unbound DNS registration. When enabled, DNS UPDATE packets from kea-dhcp-ddns are received and translated into Unbound local_data entries.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>DNS Synchronization</label>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.sync_static_reservations</id>
        <label>Sync Kea static reservations to Unbound</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Register Kea static reservations in Unbound DNS so they resolve immediately (before any client connects). Names already managed by OPNsense in Unbound (Host Overrides, or "Register DHCP Static Mappings") are skipped, so this is safe whether or not that Unbound setting is on. Requires the Kea DHCP service (kea-dhcp4/kea-dhcp6) to be running.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <id>general.general.sync_dynamic_leases</id>
        <label>Sync Kea active leases to Unbound</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Register Kea active leases in Unbound DNS with TTL matching lease expiration. Repopulates Unbound on startup and refreshes entries periodically. Requires the Kea DHCP service (kea-dhcp4/kea-dhcp6) to be running.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <id>general.general.enable_auto_clean</id>
        <label>Automatically clean stale DNS records</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <help>Periodically run the cleanup job to remove stale DNS records from Unbound (entries that don't match any Kea reservation, lease, or OPNsense-managed entry). Warning: cleanup removes ANY A/AAAA/PTR record in Unbound's runtime local-data that is not backed by Kea or defined as an Unbound Host Override — so records injected directly into Unbound by another tool or script (not through Host Overrides) will be erased. Use the Lease Audit tab to preview exactly what would be removed before enabling this.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.auto_clean_interval</id>
        <label>Auto-clean frequency</label>
        <type>dropdown</type>
        <help>How often to run the cleanup job. Only used when auto-clean is enabled. The manual "Clean Stale Records Now" button lives on the Lease Audit tab, next to the records it acts on.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>Kea-Unbound DDNS Listener</label>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.port</id>
        <label>Port</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <hint>53535</hint>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>UDP port to listen on for DNS UPDATE packets from kea-dhcp-ddns. Must match the destination port configured in kea-dhcp-ddns. Default 53535.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>TSIG Authentication</label>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
    </field>
    <field>
        <type>info</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <label>Status</label>
        <help><![CDATA[<span class="text-warning"><strong>TSIG authentication has not been tested in this release and is disabled.</strong> The listener only accepts connections from 127.0.0.1, so unsigned updates from kea-dhcp-ddns are safe on a single host. These fields are shown for reference only.</span>]]></help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.enable_tsig</id>
        <label>Enable TSIG authentication</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Require TSIG signatures on DNS UPDATE packets from kea-dhcp-ddns. When disabled, packets are accepted unsigned (safe since the listener only accepts connections from 127.0.0.1). When enabled, kea-dhcp-ddns must be configured to sign updates with the matching key name and algorithm below. NOTE: Changes to TSIG settings require clicking "Apply" to restart the daemon and take effect.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.tsig_key_name</id>
        <label>TSIG Key Name</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Name of the TSIG key. kea-dhcp-ddns must be configured to sign updates with this exact key name. Only used when TSIG is enabled.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.tsig_key_secret</id>
        <label>TSIG Key Secret</label>
        <type>password</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Base64-encoded HMAC secret. Must match the secret configured in kea-dhcp-ddns. Only used when TSIG is enabled.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.general.tsig_algorithm</id>
        <label>TSIG Algorithm</label>
        <type>dropdown</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Algorithm used to sign DNS UPDATE packets. Must match the algorithm configured in kea-dhcp-ddns. HMAC-SHA256 is recommended. Only used when TSIG is enabled.</help>
    </field>

    <field>
        <type>header</type>
        <label>Kea Service Control Connection</label>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
    </field>
    <field>
        <type>info</type>
        <label>Status</label>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help><![CDATA[
<strong>Reserved for future use.</strong> The plugin currently connects to the
Kea daemons automatically: it reads the active Kea configuration to find each
daemon's control socket (unix socket or HTTP listener) and falls back to the
standard OPNsense control sockets. The fields below are disabled and not yet
honored — they are placeholders for a future release that will let you override
the connection manually.]]></help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.mode</id>
        <label>Connection mode</label>
        <type>dropdown</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>How to reach the Kea daemons. Auto-detect reads the running Kea configuration.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.dhcp4_socket</id>
        <label>DHCPv4 unix socket</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Path to the kea-dhcp4 control socket (used when mode is Unix socket).</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.dhcp6_socket</id>
        <label>DHCPv6 unix socket</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Path to the kea-dhcp6 control socket (used when mode is Unix socket).</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.dhcp4_http_host</id>
        <label>DHCPv4 HTTP host</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Host of the kea-dhcp4 HTTP control listener (used when mode is HTTP).</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.dhcp4_http_port</id>
        <label>DHCPv4 HTTP port</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Port of the kea-dhcp4 HTTP control listener (default 8004).</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.dhcp6_http_host</id>
        <label>DHCPv6 HTTP host</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Host of the kea-dhcp6 HTTP control listener (used when mode is HTTP).</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.dhcp6_http_port</id>
        <label>DHCPv6 HTTP port</label>
        <type>text</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Port of the kea-dhcp6 HTTP control listener (default 8006).</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.http_tls</id>
        <label>Use HTTPS</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Connect to the HTTP control listener over TLS.</help>
    </field>
    <field>
        <id>general.connection.http_tls_verify</id>
        <label>Verify TLS certificate</label>
        <type>checkbox</type>
        <advanced>true</advanced>
        <help>Verify the daemon's TLS certificate. Leave off for self-signed OPNsense control certificates.</help>
    </field>

</form>
